A Finding Aid to the Agnes Anne Abbot Papers, 1921-1976, in the Archives of American Art aaa.abboagne
Archives of American Art
Agnes Anne Abbot papers
1921-1976
aaa.abboagne
Archives of American Art
0.6 Linear feet
The papers of Agnes Anne Abbot measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1921 to 1976. The collection consists of biographical information, correspondence, writings and notes, personal business records, printed material, photographs of works of art, and artwork.
Abbot, Agnes Anne, 1897-1992
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1927-1949 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1926-1951 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1930-circa 1940 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1927-1965 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1964-1968 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 6: Photographs, 1960-1976 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 7: Sketchbooks and Artwork, 1921-1965 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Biographical/Historical note
Watercolorist and educator Agnes Anne Abbot (1897-1992) was active in Wellesley and Boston, Massachusetts.
Born in Germany in 1897, Agnes Anne Abbot spent summers in the Boston area. In 1917, her family moved to the United States and settled in Boson where Abbot attended the School of Fine Arts and Crafts. From 1920 to 1963, Abbot taught at Wellesley College. She traveled extensively throughout Africa, Europe, and the United States. Agnes Anne Abbot died in Boston, Massachusetts in 1992.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Agnes Anne Abbot donated her papers to the Archives of American Art in several installments from 1979 to 1987.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Agnes Anne Abbot measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1921 to 1976. The collection consists of biographical information, correspondence, writings and notes, personal business records, printed material, photographs of works of art, sketchbooks and artwork.
Correspondence is from Abbot's family and friends and includes some letters written by Abbot to her mother, sister, and brother. Other correspondents include Alfred Barr, Alice Van Vechten Brown, Bernard Heyl, and Douglas McKee. Artwork includes ten sketchbooks depicting Abbot's travels throughout Europe, Africa, and the United States.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives of American Art holds an oral history with Agnes Anne Abbot conducted by Robert Brown on August 25, 1981 to January 15, 1982.
Barr, Alfred H., Jr., 1902-1981; Brown, Alice Van Vechten; Heyl, Bernard Chapman, 1905-; McKee, Douglas; Educators -- Massachusetts; Photographs; Sketchbooks; Watercolorists--Massachusetts; Women artists--Massachusetts
- Biographical Material, 1927-1949; Series 1; 3 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found are travel materials including airline tickets, vaccination records, and an Italian visa and museum pass.
  - Airline Tickets, 1936-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Vaccination Records, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Italian Visa and Museum Pass, 1927-1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1926-1951; Series 2; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Found is correspondence from Agnes Anne Abbot's family and friends. A letter from Alfred Barr advises Abbot on contacts in Paris. Also found are letters from Agnes to her siblings, Mary and Frank, and to her mother. Many of the letters from 1946 are condolence letters to Agnes regarding the death of her mother.
  - Family Correspondence, 1927-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Frank Abbot
    Mary Abbot
    Mary O. Abbot
  - A, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    American Red Cross
  - B, 1926-1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Alfred Barr
    Mrs. Henry Beerits
    Alice Van Vechten Brown
  - D, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    L. Deheneman
  - G, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Agnes Olney Gilmore
  - H, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Enid Heidbraden
    Bernard C. Heyl
    Mildred Horton
  - M, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Douglas McKee
  - P, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Kate Pigott
  - R, 1942-1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Adele Robinson
  - S, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Marielle (?) Solbrig
  - W, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Ola E. Winslow
  - First Names Only, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1930-circa 1940; Series 3; 3 Folders Box 1
  Found are scattered writings by Agnes Abbot regarding the art department at Wellesley College and notes. Also found are poems written by Adele Robinson.
  - Regarding Art Department, by Agnes Abbot, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Notes, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Poetry, by Adele Robinson, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Personal Business Records, 1927-1965; Series 4; 2 Folders Box 1
  Found are materials regarding travel including financial notes and receipts.
  - Receipts, 1927-1965 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Financial Notes, circa 1940-circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Printed Material, 1964-1968; Series 5; 2 Folders Box 1
  Found is a magazine clippings and information regarding travel to Jerusalem.
  - Clipping, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Jerusalem Information, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Photographs, 1960-1976; Series 6; 4 Folders Box 1
  Found are photographs and slides of works of art. Included are five photos of works of art shown at the Jewett Arts Center in Wellesley, MA.
  - Works of Art, Shown at Jewett Arts Center, Wellesley College, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Works of Art, 1960-1976 (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
- Sketchbooks and Artwork, 1921-1965; Series 7; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Found are loose sketches and 10 sketch books by Agnes Abbot. Also found are scattered unsigned sketches. Sketchbooks date from 1921-1965, and illustrate Abbot's travels in the United States and abroad. They contain drawings of street scenes, city and landscapes, sculptural and architectural details, people, and animals. 7 of the 10 sketchbooks are of Italy. Also included are sketches of Germany (including one entitled "Nazis collecting" that depicts Nazi soldiers with donation buckets on a street with pedestrians), Spain, Africa, and within the U.S. rural scenes of Colorado and Iowa.
  - Loose Sketches, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Sketchbook, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Sketchbook, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Sketchbook, 1927 or 1928 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Sketchbook, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Sketchbook, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Sketchbook, Dismantled, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Sketchbook, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sketchbook, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Loose Sketches, Unsigned, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 8)